<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<electorates>

  <state id="Overview">
    <profile>
		<p>The looming federal election will complete the six-year Senate cycle as reset by the double dissolution election of July 2, 2016, after which the twelve Senators elected for each state were divided into six serving three-year terms and six serving six-year terms (the two Australian Capital Territory and two Northern Territory Senators being an exception, as they serve three-year terms tied to the term of the House of Representatives). This determination was made by a vote of the Senate itself, with the major parties agreeing to follow past practice in allocating the longer terms to those elected earliest in the count. The three-year terms ended in mid-2019, at which point the Senate result from the May 2019 election took effect. The six-year terms are shortly to end in mid-2022, requiring an election to replace them in the year before that time.</p>
		<p>The 2016 double dissolution and 2019 half-Senate elections were held under new rules that abolished group voting tickets, whereby voters using the above-the-line section of the ballot paper numbered one party and accepted the nominated preferences of that party in full. This system proved open to manipulation from &#8220;preference harvesting&#8221; networks of micro-parties, producing results as arbitrary as Ricky Muir's win for the Australian Motoring Enthusiasts Party in Victoria in 2013 from 0.5% of the statewide vote. The new system, introduced by the then Turnbull government with the support of the Greens and over the opposition of Labor, directs above-the-line voters to number at least six party boxes, with preferences exhausting rather than passing on to unnumbered parties.</p>
		<p>As well as putting an end to the election of seemingly random micro-party candidates from tiny shares of the vote, the new system promised to deliver the government a smaller and more manageable Senate cross-bench than had become the norm since 2010. However, this was not immediately realised in 2016 owing to the nature of a double dissolution election, at which twelve Senators are elected in each state from a quota of 7.7% rather than the usual six from 14.3%. This benefited small parties to the extent that the cross bench increased from 23 seats out of 76 after the 2013 election to 25 seats in 2016, which was one aspect of a generally disappointing election result for the Turnbull government. Of particular note was the return of Pauline Hanson's One Nation to parliament for the first time since 2005 with four seats.</p>
		<p>With the higher quota of a half-Senate election in place in 2019, the result was more akin to what had been typical before 2010, despite the major party vote remaining at an historic low. With 38.0% of the Senate vote nationally, the Liberal won 19 of the 40 seats up for election and emerged in a much stronger position in the Senate than at any time since it came to power in 2013. To this were added sixteen Liberal Senators continuing six-year terms from 2016, becoming seventeen in January 2020 after party renegade Cory Bernardi resigned from the seat he had won as a Liberal in 2016. Where seven small parties had been represented on the cross bench after both the 2013 and 2016 elections, only four remained after Bernardi's departure. One Nation and the Centre Alliance (formerly the Nick Xenophon Team) both lost seats at the 2019 election, although the Greens retained their existing nine after winning a seat in each state.</p>
		<p>With the Senate consisting of an even 76 members and its President having an ordinary (deliberative) rather than a casting vote, the Morrison government's 36 seats have left it needing two extra votes for a tie, allowing opposition-backed motions to be resolved in the negative, and three for an affirmative vote needed to pass legislation. Where Labor and the Greens have been united in opposition, this has been achievable through combinations of the two One Nation Senators from Queensland, the two elected as Centre Alliance Senators for South Australia (one of whom, Rex Patrick, has sat as an independent since August 2020) and Jacqui Lambie from Tasmania. However, Liberal Senators Gerard Rennick and Alex Antic complicated matters from late 2021 through their refusal to vote for government legislation in protest against vaccine mandates.</p>
		<p>For the Liberal, the likely best case scenario for the election involves three seats in each state and one in each territory, barring a seemingly unlikely repeat of 2004 when the Liberals and Nationals won four seats between them in Queensland, which boosted the Howard government to a Senate majority. This would improve on the 2019 result only in that the Liberals would win three rather than two seats in Tasmania, where their task will be made easier by the fact that Jacqui Lambie is not up for re-election this time. However, a substantial drop in the Liberal vote in any given state could potentially put the third candidates on their tickets under pressure.</p>
		<p>The long-term decline in Labor's primary vote has reduced it to an historically weak position. It has failed to win three seats in any state at the last two regular half-Senate elections, and on multiple occasions has been reduced to a single seat, a hitherto unthinkable outcome. Partly this reflects competition from the Greens, who in 2019 won Senate seats in all six states for only the second time. Given the effective impossibility of a majority, the favoured Senate scenario for an incoming Labor government would be for the Greens to hold the balance of power in their own right, requiring Labor and the Greens to win three more seats between them than in 2019. The best opportunities would appear to include Victoria, whose leftward lean could potentially translate into four seats for the left and two for the right, and Queensland, the one state where Labor and the Greens failed to win three seats between them in 2019.</p>
		<p>Another possibility is that the Australian Capital Territory will swing far enough against the Liberals to deprive them of one of the two seats there, which would be without precedent since the territories were first granted Senate representation in 1975. However, the beneficiary of such an outcome might not be the Greens but one of two candidates who form part of a broader movement of independents challenging the Liberals on a climate activist platform. The Liberals also face a threat on the opposite flank from Clive Palmer's United Australia Party and the Liberal Democrats, both seeking to capitalise on opposition to public health measures to tackle the COVID-19 epidemic.</p>
    </profile>
  </state>

  
  <state id="NSW">
    <profile>
		<p>Explanation</p>
		
		<h3>Liberal</h3>
		
		<!-- <img src="pics/nsw-lnc.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		The agreement between the Liberal parties in New South Wales reserves the first and third positions on the ticket to the Liberals and the second to the Nationals. The three Liberal Senators allocated six-year terms in 2016 were two Liberals, Marise Payne and Arthur Sinodinos, and a National, Fiona Nash. Nash was disqualified in October 2017 during the Section 44 crisis, resulting in a recount that elevated Liberal Senator Concetta Fierravanti-Wells from a three-year to a six-year term, which amounted to the Liberals gaining a seat from the Nationals. This left three Liberal incumbents chasing preselection for two winnable seats for the coming election, the other being Jim Molan, who filled the vacancy caused by Arthur Sinodinos's appointment as ambassador to the United States after himself failing to win re-election in 2019.</p>
		<p>The vote of the Liberal Party state council in late March allocated top position to Payne and number three to Molan, reducing Fierravanti-Wells to an unwinnable position. Days later, Fierravanti-Wells told parliament that Scott Morrison, who had long been a factional enemy, was &#8220;not fit to be Prime Minister&#8221;, accusing him of being &#8220;ruthless&#8221; and &#8220;his so-called faith as a marketing research&#8221;. The result brings down the curtain on a career that began with her election in 2004 and continued after Malcolm Turnbull helped ensure she held a safe position at 2016 election, which did not discourage her from joining other factional conservatives in supporting Peter Dutton's bid to oust him from the leadership in September 2018.</p>
		<p>The Senate career of <b>Marise Payne</b> began when she filled a casual vacancy in 1997, and continued after her re-election from third on the ticket in 2001 and 2007. She survived a preselection challenge on the latter occasion from Scot Macdonald, the state party's rural vice-president, after an intervention by John Howard. Her hitherto modest political career than went into an upswing, with promotion to parliamentary secretary after the 2007 election defeat and the outer shadow ministry when Tony Abbott became leader in December 2009, leading to the position of Human Services Minister when the Abbott government came to power in 2013.</p>
		<p>Payne won promotion to cabinet as Defence Minister when Malcolm Turnbull deposed Abbott in September 2015, and headed the Liberal Senate ticket in 2016. She has served as Foreign Minister since Scott Morrison's rise to the leadership in August 2018, further becoming Minister for Women after the 2019 election. A former vice-chair of the Australian Republican Movement, Payne is part of the moderate wing of the New South Wales Liberal Party, and lined up against Tony Abbott and Peter Dutton during the party's 2015 and 2018 leadership crises.</p>
		<p>The Liberal arrangement allocates the second and third seat to the Nationals at alternating elections, this election being their turn for second. The party accordingly seems certain to recover the seat it lost as a result of Fiona Nash's disqualification in 2017. The party's candidate is <b>Ross Cadell</b>, a former state party director who won a preselection vote by 42-39 against a comeback bid by John Anderson, who was party leader and Deputy Prime Minister from 1999 to 2005 and member for the now-abolished regional New South Wales seat of Gwydir from 1989 to 2007.</p>
		<p>Third position goes to <b>Jim Molan</b>, who before entering the Senate in 2017 played a senior role in the Abbott government's efforts to stop asylum seeker boat arrivals, and was earlier a senior army officer who served as chief of operations for the Liberal forces in Iraq from 2004 to 2008.	Molan's on-and-off Senate career began after he was given the seemingly unwinnable seventh position on the ticket in 2016, with conservative backers including Tony Abbott highly critical that he was not placed higher. However, the position turned to his favour after the High Court disqualified Nationals Senator Fiona Nash on Section 44 grounds in October 2017, and further ruled ineligible Liberal colleague Hollie Hughes, who had failed to win election from the sixth position. This meant Molan won the fifth Liberal seat in an ensuing recount, and duly served out the remainder of a three-year term.</p>
		<p>Molan managed only the unwinnable fourth position at the 2019 election, intensifying complaints from his fellow conservatives about the dominance of an alliance between moderates and the centre right. A campaign for Liberal voters to trump the decision by voting for Molan below-the-line had only limited success, and roused considerable anger from the Nationals, as his seat would have come at the expense of third-placed Perin Davey if he had succeeded. A new opportunity emerged for Molan the following November when Arthur Sinodinos resigned, and he won the preselection to fill the vacancy ahead of state party director Richard Shields by 321 votes to 260. His pursuit of another term came despite the fact that he is 71 and fighting what he described as an aggressive form of prostate cancer.</p> -->
		
		<h3>Labor candidates</h3>
		
		<!-- <p><img src="pics/nsw-alp.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		Labor's ticket in 2016 was headed by Sam Dastyari, who resigned from the Senate in December 2017 after a series of embarrassments involving his dealings with businessmen linked to the Chinese government. The vacancy for his six-year term was filled by Kristina Keneally, who will now run for the lower house seat of Fowler. This leaves the other two Labor Senators allocated six-year terms in 2016, Jenny McAllister and Deborah O'Neill, seeking re-election at the top of the Labor ticket. The party's preselection had yet to be finalised as of the end of 2021, but there has been no suggestion that O'Neill or McAllister will be challenged within their factions for the first and second positions that are respectively mandated to the Right and Left.</p>
		<p><b>Deborah O'Neill</b> is a former education teacher at the University of Newcastle who held the Central Coast region lower house seat of Robertson from 2010 to her defeat in 2013. Her parliamentary career resumed the following November when she filled the Senate vacancy created by Bob Carr's retirement. O'Neill held parliamentary secretary rank through the 2016 to 2019 parliamentary term, but has since been on the back bench. She has nonetheless retained the favour of the Right, in particular the Shop Distributive and Allied Employees Association, to the extent that she was thought likely to defeat Kristina Keneally for the Right-mandated top position. This would have reduced Keneally to third, second being mandated to the Left, which prompted her contentious bid for the lower house seat of Fowler.</p>
		<p><b>Jenny McAllister</b> was technical director of a civil engineering firm when she came to the Senate in May 2015 as the Left's nominee to fill the vacancy of factional stalwart John Faulkner, and had also been the party's national president. She was promoted to parliamentary secretary rank in August 2018, which she has since retained.</p> -->
		
		<h3>Other candidates</h3>
			
		<!--<p><img src="pics/nsw-grn.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		New South Wales is one of three states in which the Greens have a realistic opportunity to gain a Senate seat, since their sole winner in 2016, Lee Rhiannon, was only allocated a three-year term. Rhiannon retired in August 2018 and was replaced by Mehreen Faruqi, who was re-elected in 2019. This leaves the party with a new candidate in <b>David Shoebridge</b>, a former lawyer and Woollahra councillor who has been a member of the New South Wales Legislative Council since 2010, having led the party's ticket at the 2011 and 2019 state elections. Shoebridge won the party's Senate preselection ahead of Amanda Cohn, the deputy mayor of Albury, and Rachael Jacobs, a lecturer in creative arts education at Western Sydney University.</p>
		<p>Further candidates include <b>Pete Evans</b>, celebrity chef and anti-vaccinationist, who is running with former One Nation Senator Rod Culleton's Great Australian Party; <b>Steve Keen</b>, an economist long noted for bearish views on the property market, for the New Liberals; and <b>John Ruddick</b>, a former libertarian-conservative activist in the Liberal Party, for the Liberal Democrats.</p> -->
    </profile>
  </state>

  
  <state id="VIC">
    <profile>
		<p>Victoria's record as an electorally progressive state is recently acquired, and has only been clearly reflected in Senate results since the Greens' first win in 2010. The Greens gained a second seat in 2013 and retained it at the double dissolution election in 2016. The lower quota on the latter occasion also helped media personality Derryn Hinch to a three-year term, followed by a more historically typical result of three Liberal, two Labor and one Greens in 2019.</p>
		<p>The potential of the state's leftward lean to convert into four seats for the left and two for the right was thwarted in 2010 and 2013 by the micro-party phenomenon, with seats respectively being won by John Madigan of the Democratic Labor Party and Ricky Muir of Australian Motoring Enthusiasts, limiting Labor and the Greens to three between them. The balance went the other way in 2004, when Steve Fielding of Family First won a seat in addition to three for the Liberal in a result that heralded the era of micro-party preference harvesting. The restoration of the left-right balance in 2007 came to the advantage of a third Labor candidate rather than the Greens, despite their vote climbing to 10.1%, their highest ever share in a losing result.</p>
		<p>The division of the twelve Senators into three-year and six-year terms after the 2016 double dissolution resulted in three Liberal, two Labor and one Greens Senator getting six-year terms, with three-year terms going to two from the Liberal, two from Labor and one from the Greens, along with Derryn Hinch. This resulted from an agreement between the Liberal and Labor to conduct the division on terms favourable to their own interests at the expense of Hinch's. The Liberal accordingly needs to defend three seats at the coming election to preserve the status quo, in a state where polling suggests COVID-19 libertarians like Clive Palmer's United Australia Party are gaining support at their expense.</p>
		
		<h3>Liberal candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/vic-lnc.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		The three Liberal Senators allocated six-year terms in 2016 were two Liberals, Mitch Fifield and Scott Ryan, and one National, Bridget McKenzie. Fifield quit politics three months after the 2019 election to become permanent representative to the United Nations, and his vacancy was filled by Sarah Henderson, who now leads the Liberal ticket. Scott Ryan followed suit in October 2021, taking up the position of high commissioner to Canada, and his vacancy was filled by Greg Mirabella, who now faces re-election.</p>
		<p><b>Sarah Henderson</b> came to the Senate in September 2019, four months after being unseated in her Surf Coast region seat of Corangamite. She is the daughter of former state Liberal MP Ann Henderson, and came to politics with an established profile as a former presenter of the Victorian edition of the ABC's 7.30 Report. After gaining Corangamite for the Liberals in 2013, Henderson seemed to be swimming against its long-term tide, and was tipped out after an unfavourable redistribution and a small swing to Labor. She was promoted to parliamentary secretary rank as Assistant Minister for Social Services, Housing and Disability Services when Scott Morrison became Prime Minister in August 2018, but has been on the back bench since entering the Senate. She is believed to have supported Malcolm Turnbull against both Tony Abbott in September 2015 and Peter Dutton in August 2018, and to have have supported Morrison over Dutton in the second round.</p>		
		<p><b>Bridget McKenzie</b> was a Leongatha school teacher and university lecturer before being elected as the sole Victorian Nationals Senator in 2010. Her predecessor was Julian McGauran, who had deprived the party of the seat in 2006 when he defected to the Liberals. McKenzie won promotion to cabinet in December 2017 in the rural health, sport and regional communications porfolios, exchanging the first two for regional services in August 2018 and the third for agriculture after the 2019 election. She also became the Nationals deputy leader at the time of the 2017 promotion, and party leader in the Senate after the 2019 election. Her ministerial career was interrupted in February 2020 after an Auditor-General's report criticised her handling of a $100 million sports grant program, causing her to resign from all her positions except party leader in the Senate. However, she returned to cabinet in July 2021 in the emergency management and regionalisation portfolios.</p>
		<p>Third position on the ticket is held by newly installed Liberal Senator <b>Greg Mirabella</b>, a farmer from Wangaratta and the husband of former Indi MP Sophie Mirabella. Mirabella reportedly won the final round of the preselection ballot to succeed Scott Ryan by 165 votes to 141 over Simon Frost, staffer to Josh Frydenberg and former state party director.</p>
		
		<h3>Labor candidates</h3>
		<p>Labor's already turbulent preselection process was tragically up-ended on March 10 by the sudden death of Kimberley Kitching, who was facing re-election to a position she had held since filling Stephen Conroy's vacancy in October 2016. Kitching was a close ally of Bill Shorten, who waited with her husband Andrew Landeryou for the undertaker's van to arrive after her death. There followed a barrage of media coverage relating to Kitching's internal struggle in the party, with the implication that the stress she was under from threats to her preselection may have contributed to her death (albeit that much of the coverage related to events that occurred in 2019, particularly allegations she had suffered bullying at the hands of fellow Senators Penny Wong, Kristina Keneally and Katy Gallagher).</p>
		<p>Most if not all of the media coverage surrounding Labor's preselection process had to that point focused on the security of Kim Carr, who had served in the Senate since 1993 and long been a figure of influence within Victorian Labor's Socialist Left faction. However, the positions of both Carr and Kitching had been weakened by the aftermath of the branch-stacking controversy surrounding Victorian MLC Adem Somyurek, which prompted an intervention by the party's national executive to take over the entire federal preselection process. This ensured the process would be shaped by a factional stability pact between parts of the Right and Left, each of whom are mandated one of the two positions at the top of the Senate ticket, that excluded the sub-factions associated with Bill Shorten and Kim Carr. However, South Australian Senator and Right faction powerbroker Don Farrell said he did not consider Kitching's position was under threat.</p>
		<p>The national executive's choice to replace Kitching, both for what little remained of her Senate term and to take the Right's position at the top end of the ticket, was <b>Jana Stewart</b>, a Muthi Muthi and Wamba Wamba woman and until recently the deputy secretary at the Victorian Department of Justice, who had previously been lined up to run in the safe seat of Pascoe Vale at the Victorian state election in November. Stewart reportedly had backing from the Transport Workers Union and Shop Distributive and Allied Employees Association, the chief Right faction parties of the stability pact. The Shorten forces reportedly favoured Natalie Hutchins, the state Corrections Minister and member for Sydenham.</p>
		<p>Shortly before the national executive made its determination, Kim Carr announced he would not seek another term, citing health concerns. However, it was widely expected that he would lose the position to <b>Linda White</b>, retired former assistant national secretary of the Australian Services Union, who was duly chosen. Aspirants at earlier stages of proceedings included Ryan Batchelor, executive director of the McKell Institute and son of former state government minister Ryan Batchelor, and Josh Bornstein, an industrial relations lawyer and Maurice Blackburn partner who withdrew over past social media posts criticising figures within the party and union movement. In the event, both Stewart and White were preselected unopposed.</p>
		
		<h3>Other candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/vic_dem_1.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px; width: 20%; object-fit: cover" align="left" />
		Patrick Bateman is the leader of the Australian Democrats and their 1st preferenced Senator for Victoria. His longstanding experience makes him an interesting candidate for this election. The Democrats have been pushing hard in Victoria this year, and most experts agree their campaigning will pay off this election.</p> 
    </profile>
  </state>
 
 
  <state id="QLD">
    <profile>
		<p>Queensland's record as Australia's most right-leaning state at federal elections have been reflected in its recent Senate results, with One Nation holding two seats since the 2016 double dissolution election and Labor reduced to one amid their disastrous performance in the state in 2019. In the ten six-seat half-Senate elections that have been held since the first in 1990, Labor has won three Senate seats in Queensland only with Kevin Rudd's statewide triumph in 2007.</p>
		<p>Conversely, the pre-merger Liberals and Nationals were instrumental in delivering the Howard government a Senate majority after the 2004 election when the two between them won four seats out of six, a result without parallel in any state before or since. The state returned four Senators from the right and two from the left in 2013, when Glenn Lazarus won a seat for the Palmer United Party at the expense of the Greens, and seven from the right and five from the left at the 2016 double dissolution.</p>
		<p>In the division of the Senate into three-year and six-year terms after 2016, long terms were allocated to three Senators from the Liberal (two Liberals and one National), two from Labor and one from the One Nation, with short terms going to two from the Liberal (one Liberal and one National), two from Labor and one each from the Greens and One Nation. The 2019 election improved the Liberal's position by delivering them three seats while also preserving One Nation's second, reducing the left to one seat each for Labor and the Greens.</p>
		
		<h3>Liberal National Party candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/qld-lnp.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		The three Liberal National Party Senators allocated six-year terms after the 2016 double dissolution were George Brandis, who quit politics to become High Commissioner to the United Kingdom in May 2018, and Matt Canavan and James McGrath. McGrath and Canavan now hold first and second position on the ticket, reflecting an arrangement in which the Nationals get second position and the Liberals first and third. Third position goes to Amanda Stoker, who filled Brandis's vacancy.</p>
		<p><b>James McGrath</b> was first elected from the second position at the 2013 election, having established his reputation as a political operator as director of the Liberal National Party's spectacularly successful 2012 Queensland state election campaign. He had also been a political adviser to Boris Johnson in his time as Lord Mayor of London, but was compelled to resign for telling an interviewer that Caribbean migrants could &#8220;go if they don’t like it here&#8221;.</p>
		<p>McGrath was long thought to have lined up the lower house Sunshine Coast seat of Fairfax upon the retirement of Alex Somlyay in 2013, but he instead set a cat among pigeons by making an unsuccessful bid for neighbouring Fisher, which Mal Brough had long been cultivating ahead of a move against Peter Slipper. McGrath promised Fisher preselectors he would not use Fairfax as a fallback option if he was unsuccessful, and accordingly set his sights on a Senate berth instead. His maiden speech called for an increase in the goods and services tax, the privatisation of the ABC and the abolition of the federal education and health departments, and as chair of the Joint Standing Committee on Electoral Matters he has led the charge for voter identification laws.</p>		
		<p><b>Matt Canavan</b> is a former Productivity Commission director and KPMG executive who came to politics via as position as chief-of-staff to Barnaby Joyce, who was then the Shadow Finance Minister. He was first elected from the third position in 2013, and re-elected from second in 2016. In February 2016 he was promoted to the outer ministry in the northern Australia portfolio, further gaining resources and a promotion to cabinet after the election the following July. Concerns he may have held Italian citizenship caused him to stand aside from July to October 2017, when the High Court ruled in his favour. Canavan again resigned in February 2020, this time in support of Barnaby Joyce's first unsuccessul bid to return to the leadership, and has remained on the back bench since. He has distinguished himself as a champion of the coal industry and an opponent of renewable energy, and was among five Senators who crossed the floor to vote for Pauline Hanson's bill against vaccination mandates in November 2021.</p>
		<p><b>Amanda Stoker</b> is a former barrister associated with the party's religious conservative wing. She came to the Senate after winning preselection to fill the vacancy of George Brandis, a moderate, from a field of twelve. However, she was easily defeated by McGrath in the preselection ballot for first position on the ticket, reportedly by 212 votes to 101. Stoker was promoted in December 2020 to the outer shadow ministry as Assistant Minister to the Attorney-General, and further gained the assistant portfolios for industrial relations and women the following March.</p>
		
		<h3>Labor candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/qld-alp.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		The two Labor Senators allocated six-year terms in 2016, Murray Watt and Anthony Chisholm, are again at the top of the Labor ticket. <b>Murray Watt</b> entered politics as the state member for Everton in 2009, having previously been chief-of-staff to the then Premier, Anna Bligh. He then fell victim to Labor's near-wipeout in 2012, and worked as a lawyer with Maurice Blackburn through to his preselection for the Senate at the 2016 election at the expense of incumbent Left faction colleague Jan McLucas. Watt was given top position on the ticket. He won promotion to the outer shadow ministry after the 2019 election in the northern Australia and disaster and emergency management portfolios.</p>
		<p><b>Anthony Chisholm</b> is a member of the AWU/Labor Forum sub-faction of the Right who served as the party's state secretary from 2008 until 2014. He lost the position after the Left gained its majority at state conference, which was also reflected in Watt's elevation to top of the ticket on debut, and was compensated with a short-term position as campaign director for the 2015 state election. He won preselection that year to succeed factional colleague Joe Ludwig, and was duly elected to a six-year term in 2016 from second on the ticket.</p>
		<p>Third on the Labor ticket is <b>Edwina Andrew</b>, a Townsville-based psychologist.</p>

		<h3>Other candidates</h3>
		<p>The election of two One Nation Senators in 2016 resulted in a six-year term being allocated to Pauline Hanson and a three-year term going to Malcolm Roberts. Roberts lost his seat to the Section 44 crisis in October 2017 and was replaced by Fraser Anning, who had fallen out with the party since running as its third candidate in 2016. The 2019 election restored Roberts to the Senate, while Anning ran unsuccessfully at the head of his own party.</p>
		<p><img src="pics/qld-phon.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		<b>Pauline Hanson</b> was famously the owner of an Ipswich fish-and-chip chop and a local councillor before winning Liberal preselection for Oxley in 1996, where she emerged an unlikely winner after a letter to a local newspaper decrying Aboriginal welfare and her disendorsement as Liberal candidate. She then founded Pauline Hanson's One Nation, but was unable to win re-election to the successor seat of Blair despite atttaining national and even international fame as the face of Australian anti-immigrant sentiment, owing to the major parties directing preferences against her. There followed an 18 year absence from formal politics in which she kept in the public eye as an occasional media celebrity and seemingly half-hearted candidate at multiple federal and state elections. Fortune finally swung back in favour of her party in 2016, amid a secular increase in minor party voting and the opportunity of a double dissolution election, in which the lower quota helped boost the party to four seats.</p>
		<p><img src="pics/qld-grn.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		Queensland is one of three states in which the Greens have a realistic opportunity of gaining a Senate seat, their sole winner in 2016, Larissa Waters, having been allocated a three-year term. Waters won the party's seat at the 2019 election after an interruption caused by the Section 44 crisis, resulting in her position being filled for a time by former Australian Democrats leader Andrew Bartlett. The party's new candidate is <b>Penny Allman-Payne</b>, a departmental head at the Queensland Department of Education and the state party's convenor.</p>
		<p><img src="pics/qld-ldp.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		A notable feature of the election is the comeback bid by <b>Campbell Newman</b>, Liberal National Party Premier of Queensland from 2012 to 2015 and Lord Mayor of Brisbane from 2004 to 2011. Newman announced his intention to run in June, criticising both sides of politics over COVID-19 lockdowns and border closures. Reports suggested he had been in talks with One Nation and Clive Palmer as well as considering running as an independent, but he ultimately fell in with the Liberal Democrats.</p>
		<p><img src="pics/qld-uap.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		A crowded field of competitors for the right-of-centre minor party vote includes <b>Clive Palmer</b>, seeking a return to parliament as candidate of his United Australia Party. The mining magnate and former state Nationals campaign director won the House of Representatives seat of Fairfax on the Sunshine Coast by 53 votes in 2013 for what was then the Palmer United Australia, which further won three seats in the Senate. The parliamentary party promptly fell apart, and Palmer did not run at the 2016 election. However, he threw a second massive advertising campaign behind a comeback bid in 2019 both for himself and his party, this time with meagre results, managing only 3.5% as his party's lead Senate candidate. All indications are that his advertising effort will be more than matched this time, much of it spruiking his party's objection to COVID-19 lockdowns and restrictions and promotion of quack cures.</p>
	</profile>
  </state>

  
  <state id="WA">
    <profile>
		<p>Western Australia has exhibited remarkable consistency through the era of six-seat half-Senate elections that began in 1990, outside of an unusual result in 2013 and the exceptional circumstance of the 2016 double dissolution. The other nine elections, including 2019, have each returned three for the Liberals, two for Labor one for either the Australian Democrats or the Greens. The 2013 election was also notable in that the result was cancelled and the election held again in April 2014 after 1375 ballot papers went missing. Labor fell short of a second seat in both the cancelled election and the re-run, making space for a Palmer United Party seat alongside the usual three for the Liberals and one for the Greens.</p>
		<p>The 2016 double dissolution resulted in the election of five Liberal, four Labor and three minor party Senators, as it did in New South Wales, Victoria and Queensland. Their division into short and long-term members granted six-year terms to three Liberals, two from Labor and one from the Greens, while the three-year terms went to two Liberals, two from Labor and one each for the Greens and One Nation. The replacement of the latter at the 2019 election accordingly gave the Liberals an extra seat at the expense of One Nation. The imminent retirement of the long-term Senators means the status quo would be preserved by a typical result of Liberal three, Labor two and Greens one.</p>
		
		<h3>Liberal candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/wa-lib.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		The three Liberal Senators allocated six-year terms after the 2016 double dissolution were Mathias Cormann, who quit politics in November 2020 to successfully seek the position and became secretary-general of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development, and Michaelia Cash and Dean Smith, who are seeking re-election. Cash and Smith have moved up to the top two positions on the party ticket, while Ben Small, who filled Cormann's vacancy, takes third.</p>
		<p><b>Michealia Cash</b> is a former industrial relations lawyer and the daughter of a Western Australian state MP, George Cash. She was first elected to the Senate from third position on the Liberal ticket in 2007, then re-elected from second position in 2013 and 2016. She held parliamentary secretary rank from 2010 to 2013 and won promotion to the outer ministry under Tony Abbott, and then to cabinet after Malcolm Turnbull deposed him September 2015.</p>
		<p>Cash has since served in a shifting array of portfolios: first employment and women, then jobs and innovation from December 2017, then small and family business and vocational education when Scott Morrison became Prime Minister in August 2018. As Employment Minister she endured controversy over an October 2017 incident in which her office alerted journalists to an imminent raid on the offices of the Australian Workers Union, though this did not appear to harm her reputation within the party. She moved to her present role as Attorney-General and Industrial Relations Minister in March 2021, after they were relinquished by Christian Porter amid his legal battle with the ABC.</p>
		<p>Cash voted for Malcolm Turnbull in the face of Peter Dutton's leadership challenge in August 2018 but was then instrumental in Turnbull's demise, resigning from the ministry (together with Mathias Cormann and Mitch Fifield) on the grounds that Turnbull had lost the support of the party room and signing the petition to bring on a second spill. She then voted for Peter Dutton ahead of Scott Morrison, one of only five to switch from Turnbull to Dutton.</p>
		<p><b>Dean Smith</b> came to the Senate in 2012 after filling the vacancy caused by the death of Judith Adams, and was elected to a six-year term from third position in 2016. He had earlier been a policy adviser to then Western Australian Premier Richard Court, an adviser to John Howard during the 1998 election campaign, and principal of a lobbying firm. Smith was the Liberal Party's first openly gay member of parliament, and went on to introduce the legislation that gave effect to same-sex marriage in 2017 as a private members bill, although he had initially opposed same-sex marriage on his arrival in parliament. He had to overcome a bid by religious conservatives to dump him for the coming election in favour of Albert Jacob, mayor of Joondalup and former state member for Ocean Reef.</p>
		<p><b>Ben Small</b> is a former logistics manager at Woodside Energy and owner of a Bunbury bar and restaurant, who came to the Senate in November 2020 after filling Mathias Cormann's vacancy.</p>
		
		<h3>Labor candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/wa-alp.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		Labor's two six-year terms in 2016 were allocated to Sue Lines and Glenn Sterle, who are again at the head of the Labor ticket and in the same order. <b>Sue Lines</b> was the Sydney-based assistant national secretary of the Left faction United Voice union (now the United Workers Union) before entering the Senate in May 2013, though she had been raised in Western Australia. She filled the vacancy created by the retirement of Chris Evans, and was re-elected from top of the ticket in 2016.</p>
		<p><b>Glenn Sterle</b> is a former organiser for the Right faction Transport Workers Union who was first elected from second on the ticket in 2004, having won preselection at the expense of Peter Cook, a minister in the Hawke-Keating government from 1988 to 1996. Sterle retained second position in 2010 and 2016, winning one of Labor's two six-year terms on the latter occasion. He remained on the back bench until June 2018, when he assumed his present position of Shadow Assistant Minister for Road Safety.</p>
		<p>The third candidate on the Labor ticket is <b>Fatima Payman</b>, a Muslim of Aghan background, who works as a political organiser with the United Workers Union and was previously an electorate officer to state MP Pierre Yang.</p>
		
		<h3>Other candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/wa-grn.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		The two Greens elected in 2016 were Scott Ludlam, who quit politics in July 2017 after becoming the first victim of the Section 44 crisis, and Rachel Siewert. The two were respectively allocated a six-year and a three-year term, but the recount that followed Ludlam's departure caused Siewert to be elevated to a six-year term and the three-year vacancy to go to Jordon Steele-John, who was re-elected in 2019. Siewert retired in September to give her successor as lead Greens candidate, <b>Dorinda Cox</b>, an opportunity to establish herself before facing election, a practice commonly employed by the Greens. Cox is an anti-domestic violence campaigner and former police office of Yamatji Noongar background.</p>
		
		<p><img src="pics/wa-onp.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		The One Nation ticket will be led by <b>Paul Filing</b>, who held the lower house seat of Moore for the Liberals from 1990 to 1996, then retained it as an independent for a further term after losing Liberal preselection through to 1998, when Mal Washer recovered the seat for the Liberals. He was a police officer before entering parliament, and is now the owner of a string of Aussie Home Loans mortgage broking franchises.</p>
		
    </profile>
  </state>

  
  <state id="SA">
    <profile>
		<p>South Australia's 2019 Senate election result of three seats for the Liberals plus two for Labor and one for the Greens marked a return to normality after the disturbance caused by Nick Xenophon's arrival on the federal scene in 2007, which could potentially be renewed with his comeback bid at the coming election. In his bid for re-election as part of the Nick Xenophon Team in 2013, Xenophon outpolled Labor with nearly a quarter the statewide vote, as the Liberals were reduced to two seats and Labor to one. His refusal to engage in preference negotiations likely cost the party one of the seats that instead went to the Greens and Bob Day of Family First.</p>
		<p>Xenophon's party achieved further breakthroughs at the 2016 double dissolution election, winning three Senate seats along with Rebekha Sharkie's win in the House of Representatives seat of Mayo. However, it polled poorly as the Centre Alliance after Xenophon's failed bid to enter state politics in 2018, and now retains two soon-to-expire Senate seats from 2016 along with Sharkie's seat. Bob Day was re-elected for Family First in 2016, but the seat passed from the party's control after he was deemed ineligible to have run by the High Court. A recount elected the second candidate on the party's ticket, Lucy Gichuhi, who sat first as an independent and ultimately joined the Liberal Party, but failed in her bid for a winnable position on its Senate ticket in 2019.</p>
		<p>South Australia was in earlier times a stronghold of the Australian Democrats, who won a seat at each election from 1980 to 2001 and two at the 1987 double dissolution. The six seats split evenly between Liberal and Labor with the eclipse of the Democrats in 2004, but both major parties were down a seat in 2007 when the Greens as well as Xenophon won seats for the first time. The Greens have won a seat at each election since, although not always in convincing fashion, and the double dissolution reduced them to one seat for a term.</p>
		<p>The division into short and long-term Senators after 2016 resulted in Liberal, Labor and the then Nick Xenophon Team being allocated two long terms apiece, with the short terms going to two Liberals and one each from Labor, the Nick Xenophon Team, the Greens and Family First.</p>
		
		<h3>Liberal candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/sa-lib.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		The two Liberals allocated six-year terms in 2016 were Simon Birmingham and Cory Bernardi, the latter of whom quit the party shortly after to launch the Australian Conservatives. Bernardi disbanded the party and quit politics after its failure at the 2019 election, resulting in his vacancy being filled by Liberal nominee Andrew McLachlan. Birmingham will again head the Liberal ticket, with McLachlan in second position.</p>
		<p><b>Simon Birmingham</b> was a staffer to Senator Robert Hill who entered the Senate upon the death of Jeannie Ferris in April 2007, after narrowly failing to win the lower house seat of Hindmarsh in 2004. He was re-elected from second position on the ticket in 2007 and 2013, behind Cory Bernardi, before being elevated to first position in 2016. A leading member of the state party's moderate faction, Birmingham has served in cabinet since Malcolm Turnbull became Prime Minister in September 2015, as Education and Training Minister through to Scott Morrison's ascension in August 2018, then as Trade, Tourism and Investment Minister through to December 2020, and as Finance Minister since October 2020. He previously held parliamentary secretary rank in both opposition and government from December 2009.</p>
		<p>Prior to his entry to the Senate in February 2020, <b>Andrew McLachlan</b> had served in the South Australian Legislative Council since 2014, and been the chamber's President since 2018. A factional moderate, he won the preselection vote ahead of former Law Council of Australia president Morry Bailes and former state party treasurer Michael Van Dissel, both associated with the Right.</p>
		
		<h3>Labor candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/sa-alp.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		Labor's Senate preselection for South Australia is yet to be finalised. The two Labor Senators who were allocated soon-to-expire six-year terms in 2016 were Penny Wong and Don Farrell.</p>
		<p><b>Penny Wong</b> led the Labor Senate ticket on debut in 2001 after establishing her credentials as a lawyer for Left faction unions, gaining a position that had previously been held by the now defunct Centre Left faction. Her rising star reputation was confirmed by her elevation to shadow cabinet in June 2005, but she was nonetheless relegated to second on the ticket at the 2007 election after a change in the factional balance in favour of the Right, who had an eager candidate in Don Farrell.</p>
		<p>By the time the situation arose again before the 2013 election, Wong had served in cabinet in the climate change portfolio during Labor's first term and finance in its second. A state conference vote to assure Farrell in the top position roused a general backlash, which included Anthony Albanese denouncing it as an &#8220;act of self-indulgence&#8221;, prompting Farrell to back down and concede the position to Wong. This proved a decisive development, as Labor did so poorly at the election that it only won a single seat.</p>
		<p>Wong was chosen without opposition as Labor's new Senate leader in June 2013, after Stephen Conroy resigned upon Kevin Rudd's return to the leadership. She held the shadow cabinet portfolio of trade investment through Labor's first term in opposition, before moving to foreign affairs.</p>
		<p><b>Don Farrell</b> came to the Senate after establishing himself as a powerful figure in the Right as state secretary of the Shop Distributive and Allied Employees Association. His first bid for parliament came in 1988, when he was the defeated Labor candidate in a by-election for Adelaide. His preselection in 2007 came at the expense of Right faction incumbent Linda Kirk, who had fallen from favour after acts of defiance that included supporting Kevin Rudd's leadership challenge against Kim Beazley in December 2006. Farrell was promoted to parliamentary secretary after the 2010 election, and to the outer ministry as Science and Research Minister in March 2013.</p>
		<p>After Farrell's self-imposed relegation to second position and defeat in 2013, state MP Michael O'Brien announced he would relinquish his seat of Napier to him at the looming state election. However, he was obliged to withdraw his candidacy after Premier Jay Weatherill threatened to resign if the plan went ahead. He returned to the Senate from second position on the ticket in 2016 and was immediately elevated to shadow cabinet as Shadow Special Minister of State. He also became Labor's deputy Senate leader, but conceded the position to Kristina Keneally in May 2019.</p>
		
		<h3>Other candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/sa-grn.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		Since the Greens won only a single three-year seat in 2016 for Sarah Hanson-Young, who was re-elected in 2019, the election presents the Greens with an opportunity to increase their South Australian contingent from one to two. Their candidate is <b>Barbara Pocock</b>, an academic economist and emeritus professor at the UniSA business school who ran for the lower house seat of Adelaide in 2019.</p>
		<p><img src="pics/sa-ca.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		The comeback bid by <b>Nick Xenophon</b> restores his Centre Alliance party to prominence, after it polled only 2.6% in his absence in 2019 and failed to secure re-election for Skye Kakoschke-Moore, one of its three elected Senators from 2019. Xenophon's political career began with his election to the South Australian Legislative Council on a &#8220;No Pokies&#8221; ticket. Quickly establishing a penchant for television-ready publicity stunts, Xenophon's vote ballooned from 2.4% on debut to 20.3% when he faced re-election in 2006, further electing running mate Ann Bressington.</p>
		<p>Xenophon made a successful bid for the Senate in 2007 with 14.8% of the vote, his support perhaps dented by a public falling out with Bressington during the campaign. He polled 24.9% when up for re-election in 2013, failing to win a second seat for his party after it dealt itself out of preference arrangements, and 21.7% at the double dissolution election of 2016, winning the party three seats. However, his bid to gatecrash the 2018 South Australian state election through his SA-Best vehicle proved a step too far, with the party failing to win any lower house seats, including Xenophon's chosen target of Hartley. He has since maintained a profile as a partner of law firm Xenophon Davis.</p>
		<p>The return of Xenophon reduces another incumbent, <b>Stirling Griff</b>, to an unlikely prospect at second position on the Centre Alliance ticket. Griff is a former owner of mobile phone store franchises who narrowly failed to win election in 2013 as second on the ticket of what was then the Nick Xenophon Group, before succeeding from the same position of what was now the Nick Xenophon Team ticket in 2016.</p>
		<p><img src="pics/sa-oth.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		Another former Nick Xenophon colleague, <b>Rex Patrick</b>, quit his Centre Alliance party in August 2020 and will now seek re-election under the banner of the Rex Patrick Team. Patrick is a former Royal Australian Navy submariner who at one point was on the staff of Liberal Senator David Johnston in his capacity as Shadow Defence Minister during the period of the Rudd-Gillard government. He was chosen by Xenophon to fill his Senate seat when he embarked on his unsuccessful tilt at state politics in November 2017, but argued he had been a de facto independent when he later quit the party and that his re-election prospects would be better if he was on his own. With Xenophon's comeback announcement he publicly mused that he might instead run for the lower house seat of Grey, but has instead to resolved to run for the Senate.</p>
		<p><img src="pics/sa-onp.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		The lead One Nation candidate is <b>Jennifer Game</b>, an adviser to Pauline Hanson who has worked as head of secrecy at the Australian Taxation Office and registrar of collections at the Australian War Memorial. Game's daughter, veterinarian Sarah Game, appears at the time of writing likely to win a seat in the South Australian Legislative Council following the March 19 election, a development that has confounded journalists given her near total lack of a public profile.</p>
	</profile>
  </state>

  
  <state id="TAS">
    <profile>
		<p>Tasmania's Senate election results have been distinguished in recent decades by the consistent success of the Greens, and more recently in providing a seat for Jacqui Lambie. It has also been the only state in which Labor and the Greens have won more than half the seats between them, with Labor winning three in addition to the Greens' one in 2007 and 2010, and five in addition to the Greens' two at the 2016 double dissolution. The Greens have held at least one seat since 1996 and two since 2004, though the party's support has fallen off from the peaks achieved under Bob Brown in 2007 and 2010, which has also been reflected at state elections.</p>
		<p>The eight six-seat half-Senate elections from 1990 to 2010 each returned one non-major party member, that being Brian Harradine in 1993 and 1998, who served as an independent from 1975 until his retirement in 2005. Harradine's victories came at the expense of a third Liberal, whereas those of the Australian Democrats in 1990 and the Greens in 1996, 2001 and 2004 limited Labor to two seats. This was followed by a high-water mark for Labor in 2007 and 2010, when Greens victories instead reduced the Liberals to two seats.</p>
		<p>The mould was broken with the upsurge in small party activity in 2013, when both Liberal and Labor were reduced to two seats and Jacqui Lambie was elected for the first time as the Palmer United Party candidate. Lambie has twice been elected since under the banner of the Jacqui Lambie Network, both with the lower quota of a double dissolution in place in 2016 and in the more demanding context of a normal half-Senate election in 2019. The latter result returned Lambie to the Senate after she fell victim to the Section 44 crisis in November 2017, resulting in her replacement by Steve Martin, a lower order candidate from her party's ticket, with whom she promptly fell out.</p>
		<p>The 2016 result was also remarkable in that below-the-line voting caused the sixth candidate on the Labor ticket, Lisa Singh, to win election over the fifth, John Short &#8212; only the second time this had occurred, the first also being in Tasmania in 1953. However, her low place in the order of election meant she was only allocated a three-year term, and she was not able to repeat the feat when again placed low on the Labor ticket in 2019.</p>
		<p>Six-year terms were initially allocated to two Liberals, two from Labor, one from the Greens and Jacqui Lambie, but the recount arising from the Section 44-related disqualification of Lambie and Liberal Senator Stephen Parry gave the Liberals a third six-year seat at the expense of the Jacqui Lambie Network, which was deprived of first preference votes for Lambie that then leaked to other parties. This left the Liberals with only one three-year seat to defend in 2019, compared with three for Labor and one each for the Greens and the Jacqui Lambie Network. The election of two Liberal and two Labor Senators in 2019 thus improved the position of the former and weakened the latter, with the other two seats going to the Greens and Lambie.</p>
		
		<h3>Liberal candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/tas-lib.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		The two Liberals allocated six-year terms in 2016 were Eric Abetz and Stephen Parry, with three-year terms going to Jonathon Duniam and David Bushby. However, both the latter were elevated to six-year terms in the recounts that followed the disqualification of Parry and Jacqui Lambie, Duniam taking Parry's position and Bushby emerging the beneficiary of the Liberals' gain of a third seat at the expense of the Jacqui Lambie Network. Abetz has now been demoted on the Liberal ticket, while Parry never returned after the particularly messy circumstances of his Section 44 departure. This leaves the Liberal ticket headed by Duniam and Wendy Askew, who filled the vacancy of her brother, David Bushby.</p>
		<p><b>Jonathon Duniam</b> is a former staffer to Tasmanian Premier Will Hodgman and Senator Eric Abetz who was 32 when elected to the Senate in 2016. He was promoted to parliamentary secretary rank after the 2019 election as Assistant Minister for Forestry and Fisheries and Assistant Minister for Regional Tourism, exchanging the latter for Assistant Minister for Industry Development in December 2020.</p>
		<p><b>Wendy Askew</b> is a former bank manager who from 2002 held electorate office and adviser positions with a series of state and federal MPs, the most recent being federal minister Dan Tehan. Her father, Max Bushby, held a seat for Bass in the state parliament from 1961 to 1986. She won the preselection that followed her brother's resignation in January 2019 ahead of Hobart alderman Tanya Denison and Break O'Day councillor John Tucker, reportedly with backing from Tasmanian Health Minister Michael Ferguson and opposition from Eric Abetz, who favoured Tucker.</p>
		<p><b>Eric Abetz</b> emigrated to Australia from West Germany as a child and worked as a lawyer prior to filling a casual Senate vacancy in 1994. Emerging as the senior figure in the state party's conservative faction, he was re-elected from top of the ticket in 1998, 2004, 2010 and 2016. He became the leader of the opposition and then of the government in the Senate from 2010, and served as Employment Minister through Tony Abbott's tenure as Prime Minister from 2013 to 2015. However, he was dumped to the back bench and from the Senate leadership when Abbott was deposed by Malcolm Turnbull in September 2015, but nonetheless retained top position on the ticket in 2016.</p>
		<p>After a further six years on the back bench, Abetz has now been relegated to third after conservatives favoured Duniam in the preselection ballot, and a view prevailed that second position should go to a woman. Abetz reportedly won the first round of the ballot for the top position with 29 votes to Duniam's 26 and Askew's 12, but Duniam prevailed by 36 to 31 after Askew's exclusion. Askew then defeated Abetz by 37 votes to 30 in the ballot for the second position.</p>
		
		<h3>Labor candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/tas-alp.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		The two Labor Senators allocated six-year terms in 2016, Anne Urquhart and Helen Polley, have again won preselection for the top two positions on the ticket, though in reversed order with Urquhart first and Polley second. <b>Anne Urquhart</b> is a former state secretary of the Left faction Australian Manufacturing Workers Union who won the faction's mandated second position on the ticket at the 2010 election after its first choice, Electrical Trades Union state secretary Kevin Harkins, was blocked by Kevin Rudd.</p>
		<p><b>Helen Polley</b> worked as a staffer to Premiers Jim Bacon and Paul Lennon before entering the Senate in 2005, holding second position on the ticket in 2004 and 2010 before winning promotion to first in 2016. A member of the Right, she has been noted for socially conservative positions on same-sex marriage and abortion. She held parliamentary secretary rank from October 2013 until the 2019 election, after which she returned to the back bench. Her brother, Michael Polley, was a member of the Tasmanian state parliament from 1972 to 2014.</p>
		<p>Third on the ticket is <b>Alison Standen</b>, who held a seat for Franklin in state parliament from 2018 until 2021, when she lost out to party colleague Dean Winter. A member of the Left, she is a former state manager of the Department of Social Services and staffer to then Premier Lara Giddings, and was Tasmanian Labor's first openly gay candidate when she ran in 2018.</p>
		
		<h3>Other candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/tas_dem_1.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px; width:20%; object-fit: cover" align="left" />
		The newest Democrats senator <b>Nick McKim</b>, is running this year for a Tasmanian Senate position. Locals report he has been campaigning the hardest, and may be the only campaigner in Tasmania. </p>
    </profile>
  </state>

  
  <state id="ACT">
    <profile>
		<p>The two territories have each been represented by two Senators since 1975, the result of Whitlam government legislation that survived High Court challenges in 1975 and 1977. Whereas the state Senators serve six-year terms that are fixed except in the event of a double dissolution, the territory Senators' terms are tied to the House of Representatives. The electoral system is the same as for the states, but it has very different consequences given two Senators are elected rather than six. The quota for election, being one divided by the number of seats up for election plus one, translates into 33.3% for the territories compared with 14.3% for the states at a half-Senate and 7.7% for a double dissolution election.</p>
		<p>A party's lead candidate is thus assured of a seat if they win a third of the primary vote, which has meant that every Senate election for the territories has returned one Labor and one Liberal member. Neither major party has ever failed to exceed a third of the vote in the Australian Capital Territory. Given the Liberals' relative weakness in the territory, the most likely scenario to disturb the status quo would be for their seat to be lost to the Greens, an independent or a second Labor candidate.</p>
		<p>The two territories have each been represented by two Senators since the 1975 election, following Whitlam government legislation that survived High Court challenges in 1975 and 1977. Whereas the state Senators serve six-year terms that are fixed but for the possibility of a double dissolution, the territory Senators' terms are tied to those of the House of Representatives. The formula for election is the same as for the states, but it has very different consequences given that two Senators are elected rather than six. The quota in either case is one divided by the number of seats up for election plus one, making a territory election quota 33.3% rather than 14.3% for the states at a half-Senate state election, or 7.7% at a double dissolution.</p>
		<p>A party is thus guaranteed a seat if it wins a third of the primary vote, which the major parties have only occasionally failed to achieve, with preferences easily getting them over the line on each such occasion. Consequently, none of the territory Senate elections has produced a result other than one seat each for Labor and the main Liberal party. Disturbances to this scenario would require a major party winning both seats by polling two-thirds of the two-party vote, or the Liberals' weakness in the Australian Capital Territory translating into defeat at the hands of the Greens or an independent.</p>
		
		<h3>Liberal candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/act-lib.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		The Liberal seat has been held since the 2013 election by <b>Zed Seselja</b>, who had earlier served in the territory parliament from 2004, where he was Liberal leader from December 2007 to February 2013. Seselja is noted as a conservative, and was among those to resign from the front bench &#8212; in his case from a parliamentary secretary position he had held since the 2016 election &#8212; as part of the move against Malcolm Turnbull in August 2018. He was subsequently restored to parliamentary secretary rank, then promoted to the outer ministry position of Minister for International Development and the Pacific in December 2020.</p>
		
		<h3>Labor candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/act-alp.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		<b>Katy Gallagher</b> came to the Senate in March 2015 after serving as Chief Minister of the Australian Capital Territory from 2011 and 2014, having been a member of the territory parliament since 2001. The seat had been vacated with the retirement of fellow Left faction member Kate Lundy, who had held it since 1996. Gallagher was promoted to shadow cabinet the following October, holding the small business and financial services portfolio after the 2016 election.</p>
		<p>The first suggestions that Gallagher might face trouble during the Section 44 crisis related to potential citizenship of Ecuador, where her mother was born, but it was instead determined that the problem arose from her mother's British citizenship. As with other Section 44 vacancies, a recount was duly held and the position filled by the second candidate on the Labor ticket in 2016, David Smith. The ACT's gain of a third seat in 2019 allowed Smith to be accommodated in the new seat of Bean, enabling Gallagher's return. She was promptly restored to shadow cabinet in the finance and public service portfolios.</p>
		
		<h3>Other candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/act-oth.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		As part of a broader trend of independents taking on Liberals in affluent seats, two significant contenders have come forward with a view to toppling Zed Seselja. One is former Wallabies captain <b>David Pocock</b>, whose environmental activism extended to an arrest in 2014 for chaining himself to a digger at a coal mine protest. The other is <b>Kim Rubenstein</b>, a human rights law specialist at the Australian National University College of Law.</p>
		<p>The Greens candidate is <b>Tjanara Goreng Goreng</b>, a Wakka Wakka/Wulli Wulli woman from central Queensland and research scholar at the Australian National University's Centre for Aboriginal Economic Policy Research.</p>
    </profile>
  </state>
  

  <state id="NT">
    <profile>
		<p>The two territories have each been represented by two Senators since 1975, the result of Whitlam government legislation that survived High Court challenges in 1975 and 1977. Whereas the state Senators serve six-year terms that are fixed except in the event of a double dissolution, the territory Senators' terms are tied to the House of Representatives. The electoral system is the same as for the states, but it has very different consequences given two Senators are elected rather than six. The quota for election, being one divided by the number of seats up for election plus one, translates into 33.3% for the territories compared with 14.3% for the states at a half-Senate and 7.7% for a double dissolution election.</p>
		<p>A party's lead candidate is thus assured of a seat if they win a third of the primary vote, which has meant that every Senate election for the territories has returned one Labor and one Liberal member. The only times either major party fell below a third in the Northern Territory were when the Country Liberals faced competition from the Nationals in 1987 and Labor narrowly failed to clear the bar in 2013, and preferences were easily enough to get them over the line both times. The most likely scenarios to disturb this in the Northern Territory would involve one or other major party winning both seats, in effect requiring it to win two-thirds of the two-party preferred vote, which has never looked in prospect.</p>
		
		<h3>Country Liberal candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/nt-clp.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		The Country Liberals have a new candidate after the preselection defeat of incumbent Sam McMahon at the hands of <b>Jacinta Price</b>, deputy mayor of Alice Springs Council and head of indigenous research at conservative think thank the Centre for Independent Studies. Price has built a high profile in conservative media, and ran unsuccessfully in Lingiari at the 2019 election. Her mother, Bess Price, held the normally Labor-held remote seat of Stuart in the Northern territory parliament for the Country Liberals from 2012 to 2016.</p>
		
		<h3>Labor candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/nt-alp.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		Labor's seat has been held since 2016 by <b>Malarndirri McCarthy</b>, a former television journalist who held the seat of Arnhem in the Northern Territory parliament from 2005 until her defeat in 2012. McCarthy succeeded one-term member Nova Peris, the former Olympic hockey player and sprinter who was contentiously recruited by Julia Gillard to replace Trish Crossin at the 2013 election. Peris and McCarthy were, respectively, the first and second indigenous women ever to serve in the federal parliament.</p>
		
		<h3>Other candidates</h3>
		<p><img src="pics/nt-ldp.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />
		Having lost preselection for the Country Liberal Party, <b>Sam McMahon</b> will seek re-election as the candidate of the Liberal Democrats, announcing her alignment with the party the week before the election was called. McMahon is a former Katherine-based veterinarian who won preselection from a field of twelve ahead of the 2019 election, succeeding Nigel Scullion, who had held the Country Liberal Party's Senate seat since 2001. She made the news in June 2021 after her unsteadiness while in the Senate chamber prompted allegations she was drunk, although she insisted she had in fact been suffering symptoms of severe hypertension.</p>
		<p><img src="pics/nt-grn.jpg" style="margin: 0px 10px" align="left" />The Greens ticket is headed by <b>Jane Anlezark</b>, a teacher at St John's College in Darwin who has taught in the past at Groote Eylandt, Arnhem Land and the Tiwi Islands.</p>
		
    </profile>
  </state>
 
</electorates>
